Hi everyone, This is the last lecture of the course and 1st we're going to continue with the topic
we discussed yesterday, virtual memory.
I'm going to continue with the hardware side of how things work in virtual memory.
And then Muhammad is delivered is going to deliver the epilogue of his of this course.
So let's start with a very quick recap.
I would suggest that you take a look at this work if you want to figure out more things about how
can we design intelligent architectures for intelligent computing systems.
Again, we argued yesterday that things should be data centric, data-driven and data aware.
And these are the recommended readings for virtual memory.
So we discussed yesterday's about some of the benefits of automatic memory management, where the
programmer does not need to deal with physical addresses at all.
And each process has its own view of a virtual address space, which is very large independent
mappings between virtual and physical addresses for each one of the processes.
And this enables code and data to be located anywhere in physical memory.
The programmers do not need to care about where data is and code and data can be shared by mapping
different virtual addresses to the same and pointing to the same physical ones.
This is what we discussed yesterday a lot.
So we would have two different virtual address spaces, one for its application, applications one and
two.
Then we would split this into chunks which we call pages.
And then we would map the pages, the virtual pages to physical pages.
And we discussed that we need a way to establish the virtual to physical address mapping, which
requires a sort of indirection.
We go through a page table essentially and we perform the translation between the virtual page
number translate we get back the physical page number and as we discussed yesterday, this is done
through the page table which is organised as a multi level radix tree.
And after we perform 4 consecutive accesses then we can retrieve the physical frame number and form
the whole physical address.
So one of the things that we discussed yesterday is like we didn't discuss yesterday's how the CPU
discovers the visual to physical mapping.
What we do discuss is.
How we serve is basically the faults and yesterday I stopped the lecture where when the DMA engine
is basically responsible for fetching your data from the disk to the memory transparently from the
processor itself.
The processor does not get involved in this process and the way the reason we do this is because we
do not want to impose more traffic and more work to the processor.
This process can happen transparently to it.
What we did not discuss and I will jump into today is the following.
So let's say that your physical memory is full, which means that your laptops are using the whole
available physical memory and at some point you need to access a new file.
So when you access a new file, the first thing you need to do is you need to find that this file is
in the disk.
So you first find the location of the file in the disk.
Then the second thing you need to do is decide which location, which physical page in memory I am
going to evict to bring in the new data and the modern operating systems can they use through LRU?
The problem with through LRU is that if I have let's say 4 gigabyte memory, 4 KB pages, the
possibilities of ordering, keeping track of metadata to figure out which was the most least, the
least recently used or the most recently used, and understanding the recency basically is something
very, very expensive.
So modern systems use an approximation of LRU to achieve to perform the replacement policy.
This is many operating systems use what we call the clock algorithm.
And there are more sophisticated algorithms which take the clock and make it a lot more advanced.
For example, the arc algorithm for from fast to 2003.
So let's see how the clock algorithm works.
So you need to keep a circular list of all the physical frames in memory.
This means that for every list, for every physical page, I have a single node that represents it.
And this node is simply a bit, one bit.
So I associate its physical page with one bit, zero or one.
I keep a pointer, the hand of the clock to the most recently used physical page.
So if this page was brought in by the operating system inside the memory, I keep a pointer to it.
And what I do is that when a page is accessed, then I set the reference bit in the PT.
This means that I will update the pointer that this bit of the page saying that, OK, this page was
recently accessed in the past.
So make sure that you probably, we probably need it and you do not evict it in the future.
So what happens is the following.
So when we need to replace a frame, so this clock, how does it work?
It starts ticking, basically trying to find pages whose bit is not set.
This means that there's a higher probability that the page will not be referenced in the future.
In this example, what happens the following?
We would start with 0, right?
We would see that this page immediately is not going to be referenced in the future.
It's at least one of the least recently used.
So this page here would be a very good candidate for replacing it.
In order to place our data coming from the disk.
If we would start from this page, if the tick pointer was here, then we would first clear the bit
because this page we need to give it a second chance that OK, this might be used in the future.
So I will give you a second chance and progress the pointer, the clock pointer.
We will do this process until we find a 0 bit.
Next time we find a 0 bit, we will replace the page, fetch the data from the disk and place them
there.
So you can think of again physical memory as a cache for the disk.
It's managed by the system software which via the virtual memory subsystem.
And the page replacement is treated the same way as cache replacement is because the page table is
essentially the tag store for the physical memory data store.
So the key difference is the following.
When I want to replace my data in the caches, I need to do it very fast.
I need a secret to basically decide which data should be replaced in the cache.
In the case of the operating system that decides, I have a lot more flexibility because I can run
software that runs an algorithm, potentially more sophisticated algorithm that decides what to
evict from the physical memory or what to bring from the disk.
What to prevent from the disk, what to proactively evict from physical memory, and all these
operations?
Second, the number of locks in a cast versus physical memory.
That creates a significant difference.
We need to we have a lot more choices to make when it comes to the operating system and choosing
physical pages to replace In the case of caches in a 32 KB cache, you have a limited number of
blocks.
In the case of physical memory, you have a huge number of pages.
And as memories become larger and larger, this choice is going to be much more complicated as well.
Also, we have a tolerable amount of time to find the replacement candidate again in the caches.
I need to make a decision right now, in the next 10 cycles, in the next 20 cycles, about which cast
line to replace and how to evict it, right?
In the case of physical memory in the disk, the process is as follows.
The disk, let's say takes 10 milliseconds to access, right?
So I have not ten, OK, that's too much one millisecond to access.
So if I have one millisecond to access the disk, I can overlap this one millisecond by running with
running an actual algorithm that predicts or that suggests some physical page to evict in order to
fetch the SSD block or the disk block.
And virtual memory plays a key role in our systems, not just because it provides this sort of
isolation or infinite memory space and all these things.
It also plays the role of the memory protection in the system.
This means that when multiple programs run concurrently, its process has its own page table.
I cannot access or view the page table of one process from another process.
This way, its process can use its entire virtual other space without worrying about where other
programs are.
What are other programs doing So?
A process can only access physical pages mapped in its page table and cannot overwrite the memory of
another process.
This provides protection and isolation and it enables also access control mechanism per page which I
will discuss now.
So as you can see here, there's an example where we have two different processes with a different
the two different virtual address spaces.
This process one is using V PVP1VP2 and the virtual address space for process 2 is using again
VP1VP2.
So what is the key difference here?
VP1 is a virtual page that gets mapped to physical memory to physical page 2.
And in this case, physical page 2 is a page that belongs only, as you can see, to process one.
However, you can see that VP 2 from process one and VP one from the process 2 map to physical page
7, both of them.
This means that they share data and the data have a specific property so that no one messes up with
this data.
The property is that it's read.
It's a read only library code.
This means that when you for example spawn 2 applications right and they want to use the same
library, let's say Pythorx, which is a very common machine learning framework and you want to they
want to they want to both use the Pythorx library.
This is going to be instantiated by the operating system as read only because if one of the two
processes changes something in the library, the other one should not see it in your operating
system course.
Later probably you will discuss how this is handled because there is a scenario here in in some
cases where process one might want to change something in the library.
So you can you need to transition from a read only state to a state that is visible only to process
one.
But in in the simplest case they simply share the physical page and everybody can read from it, but
no one can write to it.
So virtual memory implements access control and protection and it does it at the page level.
So not every process is allowed to access every page and it needs supervisor level privilege to
access system pages.
For example, when you write your C code, your Python code, you cannot access the operating system
memory at all.
Like you're not allowed to do that.
And you may also not be able to execute pages in execute instructions.
Some pages, some of the most, let's say sophisticated attacks that try to escalate privileges in
modern systems, like very high key attacks, are basically trying to execute some data that are not
supposed to be execute.
And this way you can gain for example kernel level privileges.
So the idea to prevent this is to store access control information at the.
Its basis in the process page table and this way we can enforce access control time as the same as
the same time as translation.
Which means that visual memory serves 2 purposes, 1 I translate, I find my physical location memory
and 2nd I find whether I have read permissions, write permissions, execute permissions, who has
permissions like is it a shared page?
Is it a non shared page?
I find all this piece of information and some additional metadata bits stored in the page table.
So yes.
So you can see an example again here where we have process I, it has three different virtual pages,
virtual Page 1, virtual page zero and two.
And as you can see in this case virtual Page 1 can be both read.
It can be written too and it maps to the physical page 4.
As you can see, V PVP0 can be read, you cannot write to it, you can only read it and it maps to
physical page 6.
Also, you can see that process J is the only one who also has a pointer to VP6 to physical page 6,
but this is the one responsible for writing to it.
So only process J from process J's perspective you can write to physical page 6.
You cannot write from process i's perspective to physical page 6.
And it's a nice property because this way you can have fine grained protections.
Some application, some processes can write to the physical page 6 or to memory.
Some other processes can only read from this piece of memory and these are the privileged levels,
for example, that you have in most of your systems where the level 0 can do anything.
Basically you go into a, let's say, very privileged mode where you can read and write and execute to
any memory location.
However, applications of course would not live in that space because then it would be mayhem.
So you will basically have applications beyond Level 3 where you have a paid stable for each one of
the processes and you enforce this, this access controller protection bits.
So essentially in in X86 system, the ring 0 is what we call the highest privilege, the ring one and
two, they're not widely used because mostly they're not supported by hardware anymore.
And the ring 3 is the lowest privilege where users application user applications live.
And so if you take a closer look at the page table entry of the X86 contract, then you can see the
following.
So let's assume here that we have a 32 bit system where you have two levels in the page table, the
first level and the second level.
As you can see, the PD is the page called page directory entry.
This is the first level of the page table and these are its contents.
So other its contents, it's the address of the next level of the page table and some bits here, as
you can see.
So all these bits represent this access control and protection bits.
This is a pointer to the PT and these are the flags and this is the PT, this is the last level of
the page table, the page table entry, the final one, This gives us directly the address of the four
KB frame, the physical address actually.
And these are the flags that correspond to the last level.
So the interesting part here is this that the last level of the page table as you can figure out
from this one.
Can someone tell?
Sorry.
So what is the property here?
A nice property here.
The last level of the page table covers 14 KB page.
So you can associate protection for 1/4 KB page.
The question is how many pages can I protect just by picking a flag in the PT?
Like if I set the flag here so that I cannot read any page, what does this mean for the PT?
Can someone tell me?
So essentially what happens the following PD is the second level of the page table, the first level
of the page table.
And what you achieve is that you encapsulate many last level page table entries.
So if you set the flag here to be, for example, no read, then all the pages from the last level of
the page table that you point to from the first level are not going to be able to be read.
That's the key property that is leveraged in modern systems.
Basically what?
What you can do is that you can have many of these combinations.
So if your page directory entry can basically say that this is the access type, then the PT has
another combination, right?
Some of them might be right from the user space being read only read, right?
And then you do some sort of, let's say, an and operation so that you can find the final permissions
of the page.
That's not a very important feature.
So I don't want to spend more time on that.
And what I want to spend some time is to give you an understanding of the importance of this
protection bits.
So let's say that hardware is very unreliable and I'm able to flip the access protection bits From a
securities point of view, let's say that somehow we find a way that you can, we can flip bits in
the page table, right?
This way, what would we achieve If someone goes and changes who can read pages, like whether the
page is in a supervisor mode or a user mode, then we can also flip the access control bit from user
to supervisor.
And the question is whether this can happen.
And this is one of the first, let's say iterations of Row Hammer.
And this has been shown by Google basically where you can use Row Hammer that where we can
predictably induce errors in most data memory chips in order to change the page stable contents.
Basically this was the first iteration of using Row Hammer to basically gain gain kernel privileges.
So let's do a quick recap of Row Hammer.
You can predictably, yes.
Yeah.
I was wondering then you would know where physically this page table is and then how you would know
that that's the what the attack relies on.
I will show you exactly how they do it.
They what you say is correct.
What they try to do is introduce some predictability so that you know that you're going to flip page
stable entries and not just flip a random page entry.
So they have an initial paper of row hammer.
We have shown that more than 80% of the tested DRAM chips are vulnerable.
And this was the first example of how a very simple failure mechanism, A reliability problem, can
create a widespread system security vulnerability.
And there are some news on it.
And the key idea here is the following.
We open up a row in DRAM, right?
And we close a row.
We open a row, we close a row.
And what happens is that we create bit flips in the neighboring rows.
So by simply opening up and closing a row in the middle of a DRAM bang, let's say, we can cause bit
flips in in the victim rows, what we call a victim row, which are the neighboring rows of this
hammer draw.
If we do it enough times of course.
And there are lots of follow up studies on how many times we need to do this to achieve bit flips in
the neighboring rows.
This is an example program where we demonstrate let's say errors on X86 systems.
So this is what we call a disturbance kernel.
The disturbance kernel when it executes it basically enforces it forces 2 rows to be opened and
closed one after the other over and over again.
And this way it induce many errors in the module.
And this program essentially avoids cuss heats because as you can see here, we first flash X from
the classes.
So what we do is the following.
Let me go in detail.
So we perform a move instruction.
This opens up one row, let's say it opens up row X.
Then we move Y, right?
This opens up row Y.
And then we flash X&Y from the classes.
Why do we do that?
Because if we retrieve again X&Y from the classes, then we would not access memory.
So we would need to repeatedly access memory.
So what we need to do is access X&Y many times repeatedly to induce bit flips to the neighboring
rows in between X&Y or above and below.
And this way we avoid cache hits with a sealed flash instructions and we avoid row hits to X.
If we would simply open up X, then we would hammer X, which would be an open row.
We would not close the row.
The memory controller would tell us, OK, this row is very important for me to keep alive, I will
keep it hot.
And then you would not experience row hammer.
So you need to close row X, open row Y, close row Y, open row X repeatedly like that and that's what
happens at the end.
You might have bit flips on the top of row XA lot of bit flips in between X&Y because they have an
additive effect.
In the in between rows and then some more bit flips on the bottom of a row Y and we have shown in
the initial paper that there are many errors that you can induce with different systems and we show
that it's a real reliability and security issue.
This is the initial work and this is the work from Project 0 from Google, which tried to use raw
hammer as a bug actually to gain a kernel level privileges.
And raw hammer is a problem with some very recent DRAM devices also, not only the ones from like
DDR3 and DDR4 back in the days has been shown in DDR5 very recently.
So let me walk you through the attack, the Google's original attack.
These slides are from the from Black hot talk from Google.
And the attack is actually very nice in terms of like the thinking process.
It's based on what you said actually.
It's like so the X86 page stable entries are dense and trusted.
And by dense means that you're trying to pack the physical page number, the metadata for access,
control and protection in the same bytes, in the same 8 bytes.
So they control the access to the physical memory.
Which means if I change the physical page number on the of the content of the page table entry, then
I can basically point to another memory location.
Also, if I flip a bit in the protection bits, I can change the protection.
So what do we want to do?
The aim of this exploit was to get access to the page table which gives access to all of physical
memory.
Because I can for example make a page change make with row hammer, I can change the contents of the
physical page number, and I can also change the contents of the access bits.
Which means if I make a page to be in user mode, it will be in super in privilege mode.
Then I can make it point anywhere I want, essentially.
So the key idea to avoid the problem that you mentioned is something called spraying, where you're
trying to spray physical memory with page tables.
So you're trying to instantiate many page tables in the physical memory to increase the probability
that you cause a bit flip inside the page table.
Then you try to check for useful repeatable bit flips.
So how does that work?
You're running your program, right?
And many programs do some some stuff which are very regular.
What does this mean?
So I want to map a file with read write permissions.
So how does that work?
I do in like in C or in Python, I do open like like file equals open, right?
So what does this do?
It creates a virtual page that points to a physical page.
That's the file.
But what does the operating system do as well?
It creates the page table that points to this file.
So the question is, what happens if I create many of these memory objects that point to the same
file?
Then what would happen is this.
I would create many page table entries that point all to the same file and this is what is my final
goal.
I can fill the physical memory with paid stable entries that all point to the same file.
So my physical memory at the end of the day would look like 99 five percent of paid stables and 5%
which is the file and what do they do They want to change basically one of the one of these paid
stable entries, make the correct flip, the correct bit to be flipped and then gain control
privileges.
What can we achieve with this?
If we make sure that the this paid stable is changed, then we can basically point to another paid
stable entry.
So if we change this right now, then we can basically change directly the contents of another paid
If you think about it like, we just need to make sure that we create a new direction, which means
that this virtual page, I flipped my bits in this page stable entry here.
And I make sure that right now this page stable entry points to another page stable entry by mistake
because we flipped bits, right?
So whenever, right now we write to this location, we can basically write directly to the page
stable.
And that's a obvious vulnerability, right?
If the user space program can write.
Directly to the page table, we can form any address we want, we can form any access control we want
and any protection we want.
And this way we can basically have an attacker that can read and write the page tables and they can
do anything.
After this point, their system is basically done.
So there's, let's see more issues in virtual memory, which I studied a lot during my PhD.
And the one of the most important ones that have been let's say started for the last, I would say 30
to 40 years is the concept of the concept of how we can speed up translation and access control
check.
So yesterday we discussed how we can for example establish the virtual to physical mapping.
But I did not discuss at all how the hardware does that.
I discussed how basically we can use the page table to record the virtual to physical mapping.
We discussed how we can access the page table to discover the virtual physical mapping.
But what we did not discuss is how the hardware does it on runtime.
So how fast is other translation?
So the idea is that we want to use a hardware structure at the core level that somehow keeps track
of the most hot, the most recent page table entries and reduces the number of accesses to look up
the page table.
And this is how address translation works in almost all modern processors.
So we have our core here and we need to access a virtual address, right?
The the core does not speak language of physical addresses, it speaks only language of virtual
addresses.
So it sends the virtual address to a unit called the Memory management unit, which is a hardware
unit responsible for address translation.
So it's only job is basically to talk to the memory hierarchy, to the caches, to the main memory, to
load the page table, discover the mapping, the visual, the physical mapping.
And so that the core can basically use the correct physical address and does not rely on using the
visual address which doesn't correspond to a physical location.
So the memory management unit is responsible for resolving other translation requests.
And we have one memory management unit per core.
So the MMU, we call it an MMU.
And the MMU has typically three key components.
It has translation look aside buffers, and you can think of a translation look aside buffer as a
small cast for recently used virtual to physical translations.
So we basically probe the TLB and we find directly given the virtual address, the physical
translation.
This is as if we pack the most recently paid, the most recently used paid stable entries, the
hottest ones inside the hardware structure.
Same way, the same way that caches work for data.
The second component it's paid table classes.
So I always discussed like in the last lecture, there are some intermediate pointers that you need
to walk through to reach the last level of the page table.
These pointers would lead to more memory accesses, but modern processors use page stable work *****
for the work process of the page table so that you can find the intermediate pointers very quickly
without going and retrieving them from the physical memory.
And last, there is a component called the hardware page table worker that generates all the requests
needed to walk the page table in a sequential pointer changing manner.
Does anyone have any question on this?
So this is how it looks in the system.
So you have typically two types of TLBS.
You have one TLB that caches translations for data.
So whenever we want to cut to translate data, then we go through the green TLB.
Whenever we want to translate instructions, then we go through the yellow TLB.
If we're missing these structures, then we go to NL 2 unified TLB and we call it unified because it
can cast translations for both data and instructions.
So if we in the worst case scenario that we miss in both TLBS and we do not find the translation in
these, then we need to go through the hardware page stable walk circuitry.
So the hardware page stable walk circuitry.
You can think of it as a very simple FSM in Verilog that simply generates addresses that need to be
accessed in order to fetch the last level page stable entry and these addresses we.
If they're also part of the paid table of classes, so that we can skip basically some pointer
chasing.
So the idea, let's jump to the translation look ahead bar for TLBS.
The idea is that we want to cast the page table entries in the hardware structure to speed up
translation.
And you can think of it as a very small cast of recently accessed paid stable entries.
And this way we reduce the number of memory accesses to perform the translation for instruction
fetches and loads and stores.
If we would need to go to the page stable every time we do a translation, we would need in the
modern system for memory access to do it.
If we have the hit in the first level of the TLB or in the second level of the TLB, we just perform
one hardware access directly inside the TLBS.
We retrieve the translation and we do not need to walk the page table, which means that we reduce
this 4 memory accesses to 0.
Basically this is how it works.
And this is very, very similar to how caches work.
So we're basically we have 4 different, let's say, properties, the index.
So we take the virtual page number, we take some, we mask some bits from the virtual page number and
we form the index.
And the index gives us basically the set index.
It gives us the index at which we need to retrieve our translation from.
Then we have A tag.
The tag is used same way as Cus is use A tag to make sure that this whole VPN is mapped to this
index.
And then we have data whenever we want to fetch the.
If the tag matches at the specific index, then we want to fetch the page stable entry.
And the page stable entry as we discussed before contains 2 things.
Do I have permission to access this page?
What is the physical address of this page?
And based on these two, it progresses the execution and they're the usual design choices where
there's much literature in that where we would basically try to place data, replace data, have
multi level TL, BS, etcetera.
So the problem with the TLB is that it cannot hold the whole page stable.
Think of a process that uses, let's say 100 gigabytes of memory, right?
The page stable might be 500 megabytes large.
We cannot have a hardware component that uses a 500 megabyte large space because then it would kill
all our power budget, energy budget, area budget, and everything, right?
So in some cases we need to walk the page stable watching the page table again, it might lead to 4
memory access, right?
And this would lead in return to large performance penalties.
There of course better TLB management and prefetching techniques which we can use to reduce TLB
misses.
And this is one of the last works of my PhD on how we can prefetch entries for the TLB.
But the key question is who handles the TLB misses?
And even though I told you that modern modern hardware uses a specialised circuit to generate the
addresses and the specialised FSM, this was not always the case.
For example, CPU's 30 years ago were not working like that.
In some CPU's we were handling TLB misses at the software level, not at the hardware level.
So right now the approach is hardware managed right?
So the hardware does the page table work with this specialised circuitry.
It fetches the page stable entry, inserts it into the TLB.
If the TLB is full, the entry replaces another entry.
And this is done transparent to the system software.
It's which means that I do not need to stop my application just because I had the missing the TLB
and I do not know the physical address.
So this way we can also employ the specialized structures.
I talked about the page work caches.
I can basically use some specialized caches where I find it the pointers for the intermediate
levels.
The second approach, which was used for example in MIPS based processors is a software managed.
In this approach the hardware.
If we're missing the TLB, the hardware would raise an exception.
The world would stop, the processors world would stop.
The operating system would do the page stable work.
It would fetch the PT and putting insert and evict entries in the TLB using software though not
using a hardware module.
Can someone tell me what are the benefits of using a hardware managed still be compared to a
software managed still be correct?
So it's very fast because we do not need to have a an exception.
Otherwise, we would need to raise an exception trap into the operating system, jump to operating
system software code and this would take lots of cycles.
Also, we do not need to bring any sort of new data or instructions into the caches because of the
operating system.
Now can someone tell me what's a disadvantage of having a hardware managed to still be that's a bit
more advanced, but yeah, it it, it requires hardware complexity.
I agree with this.
Anything else that's very good.
Yeah, that's one of the, that's one of the problems that like the way you would evict and managed
steel beats is going to be static.
And one more like let's say that right now I create a new operating system that has a new page table
that is not a tree exactly.
That's one of the big disadvantage of this approach.
But it's works in a static way.
If I need to change the dictionary that stores my translations, I'm done.
I cannot do it.
Basically, I cannot use any process that exists in the wild because the the contract is fixed
between the hardware and the operating system.
Now they agreed that the hardware is going to work with four level radix work.
I cannot make even the levels larger in an easy way.
I cannot have 5 levels or 6 levels.
I need to work only four levels.
And this agreement is very problematic in many ways, which I will not discuss now.
So let's see right now the benefits of software managed TLBS.
What is one key benefit of doing software managed TLB management exactly so the OS can define the
paid stable organization.
We have more sophisticated TLB replacement policies, but unfortunately, we need to generate, as I
discussed before, an exception like we need to stop the program, raise an exception and I would
have a performance overhead because I would flash the whole application.
I would fed the operating system, execute it, be more intelligent, be more flexible, but at the cost
of much higher penalties.
So let's talk right now about how the L1 data TLB works in this scenario.
We have separate L1 data TL BS for different page sizes in modern processors, which we haven't
discussed a lot about.
So one of the reasons we have different page sizes in modern processors is because we want to reduce
the number of mappings whenever possible.
If we use only four KB pages, the number of mappings we need from virtual to physical memory are a
lot.
The moment we make the page size 512 times larger into two megabytes, then we immediately reduce the
number of mappings we need.
We need to map small number of chunks from virtual memory to physical memory.
So modern Linux uses both 4 KB, 2 megabyte and one GB large pages.
But always on always.
When you configure it too, it doesn't do it without you configuring it to do it, because there are
also performance penalties associated with allocating a large page.
Can someone tell me one performance problem that that gets created when I want to allocate A2 MB
page instead of a four KB page?
That's one.
That's a very big one, yes.
So let's say they allocate 2 megabyte pages for an array that I created which has 10 elements.
Then the problem is that I would not use 80 percent, 90% of this piece of memory.
And what would be a second problem?
It's a very more hardware level problem.
So when I allocate the memory, what do I need to make sure that does not break security?
What I need to do something to this piece of memory that I allocate so they do not break security
guarantees you need to clear it exactly.
And what happens if I need to clear A2 MB page instead of a four KB page?
2 megabyte much slower exactly.
So this would basically lead to much higher what we call tail latency, which means some requests
would basically would take for them, let's say 512 extra time to clear the page compared to simply
allocating A4 KB page.
So let's see.
Write down how virtual to physical mappings are inserted into the corresponding TLB after the TLB
miss.
So one of the ways that the processor is doing it, and we're not sure about that because it's not
public information.
This is a guess basically that the processor right now is accessing all three TL BS in parallel.
So why do we need to access all three TL BS and not just for example access the four KB TLB only?
Does anyone have any idea?
Don't overlap any of different sizes.
That's yes.
Yes, but like first, do I know the page size before?
I mean we have no idea where it is exactly.
Exactly.
So the page size creates the following problem, right?
If I if I have many different page sizes and many different pages in terms of size, I cannot.
I need to guess it somehow.
I need to find what would be the correct page size and I need to guess it because as I will show you
the the offset changes when I change the page size.
What does this mean?
In the case of accessing the four KB TLB, I need to assume that the offset is 12 bits because a four
KB page has to do the part of 12 bytes right?
However, the offset, what is the offset I need to use when I use A2 MB page like?
Why do I start from here?
Because the index that I'm using in this case is 1 because this L12 MB LB has two sets right?
So I need one bit to describe the set index, and for some reason I'm using more bits here.
For the offset I'm using 21.
Yes, because like if there are two megabytes, you need to be able to iterate over every single MB
exactly, which is 21 bits in this scenario.
And when I do the same for one GB pages, I need to use 30 bits.
So in parallel I create multiple indices and multiple offsets and I act as a three TLBS.
And maybe my translation will be fine in one of those, right?
There is no chance that my translation will be fine in all of those.
It will be fine only in one or zero.
Why?
Because I would map a page only at the four KB granularity, at the two MB granularity or the one GB
granularity.
Of course, someone could say that I could describe pages that belong in A1 GB granularity at the
four KB one, but this would make things a lot more complicated.
So let's take a short break and we can continue later 10 minutes.
OK, let's see now how we can perform accesses to the L2 TLB.
So for the L1 we discussed that we need to access the 3L1 TL BS in parallel because we do not know
the page size, right?
And for the L2 unified TLB we have a different architecture in most cores.
So what is the difference here?
We only have two separate L2 TLB structures, one that stores translations for both 4 KB and two MB
pages, and what that stores translations for one GB pages.
So in most modern processors you can see L2 TL BS, a very large one that has 1.5 K entries.
Much higher latency compared to the L1 TLB because of the number of entries.
And the challenge is how can the L2 TLB support both 4 KB and two MB pages using a single structure?
Can someone think of any way like how can I store both 4 KB and two MB translations in the same TLB?
So the way to do this is by accessing.
OK, that could be that could work in some cases.
In some others it may not.
The way that one of the ways in the literature that we know of is something we call pseudo
associativity where you do the following.
You do not access the L2 till be one time but you might need to access it two times the first time.
In the first step you make the assumption that the page size is 4 kilobytes.
This way you form your index bits and the tag bits based on this assumption that the offset is 12
bits.
If the tag matches and you find an entry, this means that you've have the translation and the data
is at the fork is mapped at the four KB granularity, but otherwise you still do not have the
translation.
But you know that the L2 TLB can support 2 megabyte pages as well.
So in the next step you change the assumption and you're like, OK, maybe it's a 2 megabyte page.
So I will recalculate the offset, which is 21 bits now, and the index and the tag.
And I will access the L2 TLBTLB again with these different properties.
And if the tag matches, it is a hit.
If the tag does not match, it's an L2 TLB miss.
And the general algorithm is that I'm basically recalculating the index and the tag and the probe
the TLB for all the remaining page size.
This way I can have for example 10 page sizes and I need to check all the 10 page sizes before I
proceed in discovering that all the TLB misses and the data is not there.
So how do we do that?
We first calculate the index for the four KB page.
In this scenario we have four sets in the L2 TLB, 2 bits are used for the index, the rest 12.
The last ones are the offset.
And in this context the set 0 contains, let's say our data, right?
But let's see what happens if it doesn't contain it.
Then we need to change the index and the offset.
So we change the offset to 21 bits.
Assuming that our phase is 2 megabyte, we change the index to 01 because the L2 TLB requires 2 bits
for the set index and we're searching whether the data is in the set one.
So the advantage of this approach is that it's very simple and it's a very practical implementation.
You basically need to have a controller and FSM in the TLB that is producing the different schemes
that you need the different set index in the different offsets, right?
So can someone mention any disadvantage of this approach?
So what would happen if I only have two MB pages?
And if I hit every time in for a 2 megabyte page, then what does it increase as you correctly say?
So let's say that I hit in the TLB and I find my 2 megabyte translation, right?
But I spent 2 steps to do it.
Then what do I increase exactly?
I increase the heat latency, the heat latency, not just the missed latency, right?
So and if I miss, what do I increase?
I if I miss a lot in the TLB then I will need to spend a lot more time into performing checks.
Which basically means that if I employ 10 page sizes, I would need to put do 10 checks for
everything we missed would increase significantly the critical path of the memory axis.
Can anyone think of any optimization like how can I reduce this time while checking for all page
sizes?
Yes, you can enforce an order, but would you enforce it based on the size or based on something
else?
Like if your programme is allocating only two MB pages, do you really need to check first for 4
kilobytes?
So based on what you would enforce the order exactly.
So you would do it based on what the operating system does.
If the operating system could tell you that all my pages that I'm going to allocate for you are two
MB pages.
So do not try the four KB probe first.
Try A2 MB probe.
Probe first and another way.
Yes, which would basically be what what would be the total latency in this case?
Yes, exactly.
But like it will be the maximum of all the checks, right.
Exactly.
So that's the first way you do parallel look UPS.
You have hardware that in parallel has a circuitry where you check all the page sizes, but you need
different decoders.
You need many different things, right?
Because I need to for example bring in tags from three locations in parallel, which is a lot more
complex compared to accessing a single tag.
The second is what you have been discussing, the page size prediction.
Like if I see the operating system is allocating 2 megabyte pages for me, or I seen my history of
translations and hits, but most of the pages are two MB pages, then I do not need to check for the
4 kilobytes first.
I will just simply check the 2 megabytes first.
So now let's see how the hardware page stable worker is organised.
So this is a per core hardware component that works the multi level page stable to avoid the
expensive contact switches in the software handling.
It has mainly 2 components, a state machine and FSM that is designed to be aware of the
architecture's page stable structure and some registers that keep track of the outstanding TLB
misses.
So the worker essentially needs a log that says oh I have to service this misses from the L2 TLB and
I will have a state machine that generates the addresses for the page stable.
So you can think of it in this way and the advance.
The advantages is that you don't need to perform contact switches and you overlap the LB misses with
useful computation.
You support concurrent LB misses, but there are hardware area and power overheads because you need
to have a new hardware secretary limits flexibility.
So let me walk you through the example.
So let's see how a software paid stable worker would work and how this would lead to lower
performance compared to having a hardware paid stable worker.
So let's say that we use a software TLB miss handler and we are trying to perform a load A that
targets VPN equals 1.
So then we have a TLB miss.
And as I said with the the page table walk handler is software based.
So we have a contact switch, the operating system gets invoked here, it accesses the paid stable, it
inserts the entry back in the TLB and then we perform a load B to VPN equals 5 and we have a TLB
hit.
So in the case of a hardware paid stable worker, we again have a TLB miss.
But the key thing here is that we can at the same time perform the load B.
We can perform the load B because this did not raise an exception here.
There is a hardware component here that is servicing this TLB miss so the load B can continue and we
experience the heat which is parallelised with the page stable work process and this is what we
gain back in terms of cycles.
Now the page stable work classes, I will not go deep into this.
The page stable work classes essentially have a single job to do.
They cast translations from the entries of the page stable that are pointer based.
If I load a page table entry and it's from the first level, the second level, or the third level
which is not the final level, this entry will contain will contain a pointer to the next level.
I simply cast these pointers into the page work classes.
So there are some more let's say issues that we can cover in others translation.
And one of them is when do we do the address translation, right?
So do we do it before or after accessing the L1 cast?
Will I access the L1 cast with a virtual address or with a physical address?
So in other words, is the cast being tagged and addressed with a virtual address or with a physical
address?
And there are some problems basically and issues with using a virtually addressed cast.
Can someone tell me one of them?
So let's say yes, yes, but why do you need to do that?
OK, I agree.
So how could you change your classes to avoid this?
OK, allocating the cast of different processes is a bit of a very complex scenario.
That is one way you need to access to see if I have you need to access some bits to figure out if
you have permissions to this page.
But another easy way is that I can simply say, oh, this data belongs to application A, so you don't
have access to it as application B and you need to keep track of that in the caches.
So your tag could not only contain the virtual tag, it also needs to contain some PID, the process
ID or thread ID or something like that so that you know that this data belongs to this process and
doesn't belong to another process.
So this is what we call as a synonym problem.
This is one of the problems there is like the homonym and the synonym problems.
So the synonym problem is that you might have two different virtual addresses that map to the same
physical address and this way the physical address can be present in multiple locations in the cast
which is very problematic.
This can lead to inconsistency in the data.
That's why you would need to flash every time because you might lead to inconsistencies.
So there are two types of problems, the homonyms and the synonyms.
And in this scenario, the homonyms are basically caused when you have the same virtual address that
can map to two different physical addresses, while in the synonyms you can have different virtual
addresses that can map to the same physical address.
So why?
Why do we have homonyms, right?
Because we might have virtual addresses in different processes and synonyms, we have different pages
that can share the physical frame within or across processes.
And the reason would be shared libraries and more, right?
So a big question which I don't think I will answer in this lecture because it gets more
complicated, is whether these synonyms and homonyms create problems when we have a cast.
So everything basically depends on this.
The whether the synonyms or the homonyms create problems is when do you do translation?
Do you do it directly after the CPU issues the request and you do it via the TLBS and you determine
the physical address and then you send the data the the physical request to the classes?
Do you do it?
Do you access first the L1, let's say data class and then?
With the translation, do you somehow access them in parallel?
Which means that I am accessing the TLB with a virtual address waiting for the physical address, but
at the same time I'm doing the tag look up in the cache to overlap a bit the latencies and gain
some performance.
This also creates problems, but this is also how the process right now work.
They use part of the virtual address to access the L1D and do the to to find the set basically in
the cast.
And then they're waiting for the translation for the physical address to determine the tag and do
the tag matching.
And here you can see the evolution of the virtual memory subsystem, which in the latest years it has
changed significantly.
So back in the days it had like the only thing you had was one one data TLB and L1 instruction TLB.
And if you miss in either of those, you basically trigger software paid table work.
We didn't have a hardware ship with to do the work.
And this also how things have changed, like in AA14, let's say processor back in the days in an
iPhone 12 Pro, you might have had like an L2 TLB with 3000 entries and 16 kilobytes of page size.
While the X86 consortium like an Intel AMD ARM, ARM is not in the X86, but like it's using a similar
architecture.
It would have, let's say 4 KB pages with 1.5 K entries, right?
Completely different sort of approaches to it.
But of course, virtual memory creates some overheads, right, as we discussed, and this is what I
explored a lot in my thesis, as I said.
And we propose this simulation framework so that we are able to find out these overheads and
evaluate new techniques.
And the key idea of course was that like the, the key assumption is that like virtual memory was the
cornerstone of computing systems, right?
Like CPU's have it and network interface cars are using it, CPU's are using it, but it does not come
for free.
So we have virtual memory that causes this high performance overheads because of two reasons that we
discussed in this lecture.
First, because the operating system needs at some point to create the mapping, it needs to allocate
physical memory for the application and then the hardware needs to perform address translation.
So we have workloads like for example the lens is a good workload to think about where they are
spawned with a very high throughput.
Right now, data centres receive.
A huge amount of requests for LMS especially there is a class of them called sorting, sort output LM
inference, where the amount of time we spent on the operating system to perform the allocation is
much, sometimes a lot smaller compared to the actual execution.
For example, you might receive all your tokens in one second and to allocate the whole memory you
need to perform this inference, you might spend 2 seconds.
So basically this short execution time cannot amortize the operating system routines.
And we profiled some workloads where we show that like on average, in some cases 32% of execution
time is spent on physical memory allocation.
And the second part of the overhead is other translation overheads.
These do not appear in this short running workloads, but mostly in applications which are very
stable and have long running properties with very large data footprints.
So usually these have run, let's say more than 100 seconds, let's say a big database server where
you're sending many requests.
And if you do many operations or for example, you're running a Google search where you do page rank,
let's say, right?
And in these scenarios, you would have lots of irregular memory accesses where you cause multiple
TLB misses, multiple page table walks that basically stop you from fetching the data quickly.
You need to spend a lot of time on other translation before you can fetch data.
We showed again, this come from a real system, like on average 26% of execution time is spent on
other translation in these irregular workloads.
And together you can see that this subsystem is causing many diverse types of overheads in the
system which are expected to increase basically.
So as you can see, if you see like modern systems, you're using a GPU which has one type of memory,
this sort of HBM high bandwidth memories which are used for both gaming and like AI inference right
now.
And you have ACPU which has a much larger memory, but it's a lot more slow.
Our bandwidth compared to CPUGPU memory.
Lately we also have systems which have direct storage access.
We can access this as D directly without invoking the operating system.
We also have memory segregation which means that in a cloud scenario I can not only have access to
my local memory, but I can have access to another remote memory that exists somewhere in the data
centre.
And this way I can effectively increase my memory capacity at low latency.
And in this work, we basically had a simulation framework which we integrated with many
architectural simulators and built a specific tool that has many virtual memory techniques used in
the literature to basically validate against the high end server grade CPU and showcase multiple
use cases.
And we did this in order to discover new insights and to provide to the community a way to evaluate
these overheads in an easy way.
This is a website, you can easily get started with it.
It's very simple.
And this is the one of the works that the first work that I did on other translation, it's called
Victima.
It's one of the ways to basically extend the amount of memory covered by a TLB hierarchy by using
also the classes as a substrate for storing TLB entries.
Because right now caches in the systems cannot be used as TLBN cannot store any sort of TLB entries.
And this is the second work that I did in other translation where we demonstrate that like if we
keep the visual memory subsystem as flexible as possible, then we start facing overheads because
this requires expensive page tables, very large page tables.
So one key idea is that leverage hashing in order to map a virtual address directly to a virtual
address, directly to a physical address.
And this way we can lower a lot the size of the translation structures.
This one of the earliest works of the group where we completely rethink the way virtual memory
works.
And we have two types of virtual memory, two types of other translation, one on the front end.
Basically you do it before accessing the cast, you do one translation and then you do one more after
you access the after you access the cast hierarchy.
And you do this so that you remove it from the critical path of the execution as fast as as best as
possible.
So in summary, virtual memory gives the illusion of an infinite capacity.
A subset of virtual pages are located in the physical memory.
Some other ones are stored in the disk.
The page table is a structure that maps virtual pages to physical pages.
How?
With the process of other translation?
The TLBS in the memory management unit speeds up the other translation.
We have multi level page tables that keep the page table table size in check.
We do not store a monolithically a huge array that's a page table and if we can use different page
tables for different programs we can provide memory protection.
There is a lot more on on this topic like how do you handle other translation in AV in AVM in a
virtual machine.
In this scenario, you would use A2 level address translation, one from the guest to the host and one
from the host to the physical memory.
So some parting thoughts.
Virtual memory is one of the most successful examples of architectural support for programmers, how
we can partition the hardware and the software effectively and it poses the programmer architect
trade off.
So going forward, we need to see how to scale virtual memory in the future with four key trends.
As I said, we have huge physical memories at this point.
We have hybrid physical memory systems with both very large Intel obtained.
For example, if you have seen and like DDR interfaces, we have many accelerators like GPU's and
other components.
And also we have virtualised systems.
We've virtualised a lot, a lot more, which complicates the virtual memory.
There's some lectures on it as well.
I would suggest taking a look at that if you're very interested in the topic.
And I will conclude my talk and I will give the states Mohammed.
OK, Thanks a lot Constantinos.
I actually enjoyed his lecture.
I thought I know virtual memory, but today actually I learnt more.
It's a very exciting topic.
So I'm going to quickly go over epilogue of this course and we'll see if I get chance to present
future of Computer architecture.
Today is actually another epilogue also for me.
Today's going to be my last day in ETH so but I will hopefully attend your exam, so I'm going to see
you also there.
OK, so I'm going to start with some recall from this course.
So remember that we started with basically major high level goals for this course.
We wanted to understand basics, principles of designs and also precedents.
And actually we covered all of it.
So we covered a lot of principles and precedents.
We provide a lot of examples from real world, real processor, real system that people have designed.
And the the goal was to basically from this understanding, we learn how a modern computer works on
their knees and to evaluate trade-offs of different designs and ideas and to implement a principle
design.
You learn how to design A processor.
Maybe you're not that fascinated about it.
It was a kind of simple processor, but hopefully as you if you're interested, you can actually build
on it and make much more complicated processor.
Also during your labs, you learn how to systematically debug increasingly complex systems.
So a lot of labs actually was about that.
So that all of this hopefully enable you to develop novel and out-of-the-box designs.
So one of the core, I would say juice of this course was to teach you how to think critically.
So every idea that today also, for example, that Constantinos was presenting, he was asking what are
the, you know, pros and cons?
And actually he made it quite interactive, which I enjoyed a lot.
So you guys also went over pros and cons together with him, which is amazing.
And I think that was very nice summary of the course that we had.
So, and also remember that why we had these calls because essentially it's very important for
different topics in computer science.
And so with this course actually, regardless of your future direction, you're going to know how to
design better hardwares if you're interested.
Also by knowing the hardware, how cache works, how prefetching works, virtual memory, what are the
important things about it, You know, you can hopefully write better quotes and better make better
software with virtual memory.
Also understanding of that can make you better systems and also in the end knowing about trade-offs,
critical analysis, all of them would make you, you know, some skills that can use for better
systems.
So, and I would like to mention that essentially this course teaches us how to solve problems
better, how to think in parallel and also think critically.
So we have come a long way.
We started from transistors as the building block and actually we accomplish quite a lot and we get
to build up to virtual memory and system software mechanics.
And we in between actually we talked about logic design, combinational sequential circuits,
execution model, ISA, micro architecture, many execution paradigm that we also covered like out of
world, AVLIW, systolic, the SIMD and GPU and also we covered quite a lot in memory system.
So I think we actually accomplished a lot of interesting topics.
It's very hard actually to combine all these topics in one course, but hopefully this course
actually gave you quite a nice abstraction of the whole the entire stack of the competing.
So there are some takeaways that I'm going over them very quickly.
So the first takeaways that all we covered is real and used in real systems and you have seen a lot
of examples of that.
Even some of the topics like VLIW that when people design VLIW, they actually they get they got a
lot of naysayers that this is not going to be adopted, which might be the case in some cases like
in general purpose applications.
But nowadays actually VLIW has been used in some other domains like embedded systems, some
accelerators and so.
So there are a lot of similar examples that we have had in this course regarding caching and we
provide a lot of examples and also the usage of them them also in our real life that we had some
analogy that we discussed through the course like pipelining, we discussed about caching locality,
all of them that we have also in our real life.
And the the second take away actually is that principles.
We covered apply broadly not only in computer architecture and we have had a lot of examples of
that.
And most importantly the third take away is that trade off analysis and critical taking that you are
exposed to apply even more broadly.
So this going to be actually very important in many, many other things that you're doing in future.
The basically your carrier and in company, if you're doing some consulting for a company, if you're
starting a new company, if you're doing research, all of it actually is very important how to think
critically and evaluate different ideas.
So we are done with all of this micro architecture, pipelining, precise exception, out of order
super scale execution.
We have covered a lot of different paradigm of computing and we actually also look into a lot
different ways to extract instruction level concurrency.
And we visited a lot of these topics and now that you know, all of these topics actually is nice
food for thought that you think about trade-offs of these different processing paradigms.
We are also now done with these the memory organization.
So we have covered actually quite a lot in about memory system.
It's it's so you cannot, you cannot be really enough with memory system.
It's kind of endless.
You know, there are a lot of topics, a lot of challenges, but this course actually provides a lot of
basics about memory system as well as cutting edge topics like Constantinus actually, he actually
touched some very state of our topics like the papers that he was presenting to.
So now you are very familiar with memory system which is great.
And now also you can think of trade off of many different memory system designs and ideas and how
memory system is actually interacting with processor design.
So and so basically how can we optimise both a memory and processor together in a more balanced way?
Hopefully so.
And we actually had this transformation hierarchy that we try actually to have a more expanded view
of computer architecture from algorithm to the device.
And essentially virtual memory that Constantinos presented is has been known as one of the most
successful hardware software code design that people designed for decades.
And it's actually, it's been very successful.
So that's actually a very good example how hardware and software can work together to make, you
know, to make a big impact on how we write programs and how we run our programs in the system.
So that can apply in many different topics like in like in prefetching, in the how do you handle
your caches, how you handle processor.
So a lot of time you can actually benefit from this cooperation between hardware and software.
And it's also another recall that essentially this course brings learning experience, long term
trade off analysis, critical taking and decision making.
And so I don't want to repeat it again, but essentially what we saw changed the world and endured
the test of time.
And it will be more important.
You may not all be future architect, but your development and thinking can greatly benefit from the
concept trade off principles and critical thinking.
And it's important that we focus on understanding, learning and critical analysis.
And these are actually the agents for your growth.
And the course is designed to activate these agents.
And if I'm not successful enough to convince you, I also brought this quote on college education.
Do you know who's this quote from?
Yes.
Correct.
Yeah.
So the basic Einstein mentioned that it's not so very important for a person to learn facts because
facts you can learn, you can forget, you can lead, lead learn them.
But it's there are things that the value of an education in a liberal arts college, which you can
think of as a more like it can be applied to any college.
So there is a context that where Einstein was presenting this talk.
But essentially the value of an education in a, in any college is not the learning of many facts,
but the training of the mind to think something that cannot be learnt from textbooks.
So you can actually made it also at home.
Think about a lot of things that we taught this in this course and see what are the things that you
can actually easily learn from textbooks and what are the things that you cannot really, you know,
learn easily from textbooks.
And actually you benefit from this interaction in the lecture with the with the president, with the
instructors.
There are also some more quotes.
I don't know how much time I have, but let's see.
10 minutes.
OK, so I guess I'm good.
This course is also one of my favorite.
So the reasonable man adapts himself to the world, the unreasonable 1 persists in trying to adapt
the world to himself.
Therefore, all progress depends on the unreasonable man, which to me actually, this is one of the
the most complicated thing for a lot of school systems, like not only in in this country, in
everywhere, like all the time, actually teachers, they really want to make sure that, you know,
students are following some, you know, some specific things.
And there are always some students that they don't want to, you know, comfort.
And that can actually cause problems.
Like how to deal with that actually is a big challenge.
And I can say that in many, many school systems actually try, they try to make students and people
to follow similar rules, all of them.
And that is kind of against.
So we should be careful about that because that is actually kind of against of how progress makes.
So it's important to be unreasonable in some cases as well.
So this quote is from George Menard Shaw.
He also has another, he's actually an Irish person and which won novel in Nobel Prize in Literature.
And there are a lot of interesting things about him.
You can also check if you're interested.
He also had another quote which is very similar to the previous one that progress is impossible
without change and those who cannot change their minds cannot change anything.
So this actually also very important as a juice of this course, you know, how how you deal with
different ideas, how you deal with different techniques, how you critically think about them.
So I don't know if if we showed in this course, but there are some things related to, you know, how
people evaluate different mechanism and some, some reviewers, for example, they say that it works
OK, you know, why do we need to change it?
And that's completely against of this talk, this code, you know, because yes, so no progress is
going to happen at all.
So it's important to think about such things.
There's also another thing, one poem which I'm not going to read it, so you can actually read it if
you're interested later.
But I would say that actually integrity of mind is very important and that's really need to
prioritise a lot as much as possible.
OK, so let's quickly also see what we did not cover.
We actually we couldn't cover a lot of things because computer architecture is very rich and there
are a lot of ideas, lots creativity, many trade-offs and problems.
And as a scaling performance, energy, reliability, security issues become worse in circuits and in
software, computer architecture will be more and more important.
So we, we are all of these actually already obvious in AIM and accelerators in hardware security
issues in novel execution paradigms like trust in memory that I'm trying to, I will try to talk
about it a little bit today, but essentially these are very important.
So if you're interested, I would also recommend that you check memory centric lecture, memory
centric computing lecture that we had before about these topics.
So in Safari, actually we are working on many different domains in computer architecture.
And so I can summarise them actually in the in these five, let's say, major research topics.
So you've seen a little bit of robust architectures when we talk about row hammer row Press, those
stuff.
So making architecture secure, reliable and safe are very important.
How can we fundamentally make system energy efficient?
Which memory centric computing is actually one of the big part of it that essentially one of the
main or one of the, let's say dominant source of consuming energy is actually data movement.
And in today's architecture, in conventional computing we are doing, we are having a lot of data
movement because data is stored far from where we are processing.
So you need to bring data from storage for example to the to the main memory and then from main
memory to caches to the registers and then try to compute on them.
So that you there are a lot of data movement.
And we actually, I think Professor Muthu, actually, he showed some data from Delhi that the energy
that you're consuming for bringing data is orders of magnitude more compared to the energy that you
consume to operate on that data.
So that's is a lot of the the topic that essentially if you want to fundamentally make things energy
efficient, it's good to try to do computation where data resides.
So if your data resides in.
Storage, you can actually try to do compute inside the storage and that's a lot that we are doing in
Safari about storage centric computing.
Or if your data actually resides in memory, so you don't have to bring that to the processor.
You can try to compute as much as possible inside the memory and that can actually make in the end
make your system much more data centric and the the whole processing is going to be much more
balanced.
So and in the end it's going to give you better energy, better performance and also sustainability.
We also work a lot on how to make things lower latency and predictable.
So today we are actually dealing with a lot of long latency operations like long latency memory
accesses and a lot of things are that we are designing are actually around it.
Just try to hide that latency, like think about caching, like caching is to is there to hide memory
access latency or pre fetching that we have there is to hide basically try to hide like cache
misses, for example.
So but if you can try to make memory faster, then you are actually solving a more fundamental
problem, you know, and that can actually relief the system from a lot of costs that we are causing
now just to try to hide latencies.
OK.
So that's why designing systems that they are fundamentally low latency are very important.
Predictability is also very much important because we are dealing with a lot of deadlines like hard
and soft deadlines and a lot of applications they have quality of service that you need to make
them predictable in your architecture.
Also we work a lot on making system data-driven and data aware.
So by data-driven like these, today's application have a lot of data they are operating on and you
can actually use this data characteristics of them to learn how to become a better system.
So you actually see a glimpse of that in like in prefetching lecture.
I think in PTR that for example we use machine learning for for for prefetching.
Also in branch prediction, I think you learn about perceptron learning that we can use that in for
branch prediction.
So these are kind of techniques that we can learn from the system, from data characteristics and we
make a better system decisions.
Also you can think of making systems data aware, which by transferring the semantics of your data
from the software layer to the hardware like as we are also doing in hardware software code design.
Then you actually at the hardware you can make much more intelligent decisions.
Like for example, if you know that your software is late, it can tolerate some errors, then actually
you can have a, you know, architecture or memory which you can trade off some, you know, errors for
better performance, for better energy.
And if you are careful about the design of that, actually you can have a system which is higher
performance, better energy efficiency and also still accurate.
So these are actually very interesting things to do.
And also we are using these all these topics, data centric, data-driven and data ever architectures
in order to design architectures for many important applications, including machine learning, AI,
genomics, medicine, health, and so on so forth.
And we always look into the the entire stack of computing.
So it's going to be very much the core of these all these ideas.
So if you're interested, you can actually also watch this lecture from Professor Muthu that he
explained, you know, that introduce software research group in a bit more detail.
And essentially one of the axiom that we have is that we need intelligent architectures and these
architectures handles data Bill.
So we need to make sure that they don't basically this huge data amount that we have today in in our
applications.
Basically the the hardware does not get overwhelmed.
And also we we can take advantage of vast amounts of data and metadata and we understand and exploit
properties of different data.
And that brings us essentially to these domains.
So instead of designing processor centric, we can be much more data centric.
And instead of being designer dictated decisions, we can make data-driven decisions and also we can
make systems data away.
So I think I'm going to conclude here.
So architectures for intelligent machines needs to be data centric, data-driven and data away.
And that's the juice for, in my opinion, how the future computer architecture is going to look like.
So thanks a lot everyone.
I hope you actually enjoy the course.
And this is going to be the last lecture, I guess.
I guess in a in a way that they're going to be hopefully some problem solving sessions as well.
Also before the exam.
I think the exam is sometime in August.
I don't know the exact date but yeah, I hope.
Hope you you study well and prepare for the exam.
Don't worry much about the exam.
I think you're going to do a great job there.
And yeah, and I wish you also the best.
I hope you also have some time to, you know, have a good semester break as well.
So enjoy your time.
Don't think much about the exam.
And yeah, and wish you all the best.
Thank you.